Luther Henderson Papers
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Luther Henderson Papers circa 1930-2003 (bulk 1960-1995)
ML31.H45
Henderson, Luther, 1919-2003
approximately 17,250 items 128 containers 54.5 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Luther Henderson was an American arranger, orchestrator, conductor, music director, and composer. He worked on over fifty Broadway musicals, including Ain't Misbehavin' and Jelly's Last Jam. He was a frequent arranger and orchestrator for Duke Ellington. The collection contains music manuscripts, correspondence, business and financial papers, photographs, promotional materials, clippings, realia, and other materials related to his career.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Burr, Charles.; Citron, Stephen.; Ellington, Duke, 1899-1974.; Fleagle, Brick.; Fleagle, Brick.; Henderson, Luther, 1919-2003--Archives.; Henderson, Luther, 1919-2003--Correspondence.; Henderson, Luther, 1919-2003--Manuscripts.; Henderson, Luther, 1919-2003--Photographs.; Henderson, Luther, 1919-2003.; Henderson, Luther, 1919-2003.; Henderson, Luther, 1919-2003. Selections.
Organizations
Canadian Brass.; Royal Philharmonic Orchestra.
Subjects
African American composers.; Arrangers (Musicians)--United States.; Jazz--Lead sheets.; Jazz.; Music--Manuscripts--United States.; Musicals--Excerpts.; Musicals--Scores.; Orchestrators--United States.; Popular music--United States.; Revues--Scores.; Revues.
Titles
Ain't misbehavin'.; Ain't misbehavin'. Selections.; Jelly's last jam.; Jelly's last jam. Selections.
Form/Genre
Artifacts (Object genre); Clippings (Information artifacts); Correspondence.; Financial records.; Notes.; Photographic prints.; Programs (Documents); Promotional materials.; Scripts (Documents)
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift, Billie Allen, 2005.
Accruals
Further accruals are possible.
Transfers
Sound recordings from the Luther Henderson Papers have been transferred to the Library of Congress Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. An inventory of this material is available in the collection file.
Other Repositories
The Peabody Institute of the Johns Hopkins University holds Brick Fleagle's extensive jazz sound recording collection, which Henderson donated to the Institute in 1993.
Related Material
The Music Division holds several special collections that contain Henderson arrangements and correspondence, including the
Billy Byers Collection
, the
Billy Taylor Papers
, and the
Richard Rodgers Collection
. The William P. Gottlieb Collection contains photographs of Henderson's friend and fellow arranger Brick Fleagle.
Access and Restrictions
The Luther Henderson Papers are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1919, Mar. 14 Born, Kansas City, Mo.
1936-1938 Attended College of the City of New York
1939, June 17 Married Tealene Nee Berry
1940, Dec. 24 Son Denson born
1942 B.S., in music, Juilliard School of Music, New York, N.Y.
1944-1946 Staff orchestrator, U.S. Navy School of Music, Washington, D.C.
1946-1947 M.A., in music, New York University
1950, Mar. 19 Son Luther born
1956, Sept. 14 Married Stevie (Muriel) Melzer
1957, Sept. 20 Daughter Melanie born
1958 Composed arrangements for Rodgers and Hammerstein's Flower Drum Song
1960 Composed arrangements for Do Re Mi
1971, Jan. 30 Married Margo Semos
1978 Arranger and orchestrator for Ain't Misbehavin'
1981, Feb. 8 Married actress Billie Allen
1988-1989 Conducted and played piano for Broadway revival of Ain't Misbehavin'
1992 Jelly's Last Jam nominated for Tony Award for best score
1992 Jelly's Last Jam wins Drama Desk Award for outstanding orchestration
1997 Play On! nominated for Tony Award for best orchestration
1999-2000 Collaborated with Sir Simon Rattle, Lena Horne, and the City of Birmingham Symphony Orchestra on performances and recordings of Classic Ellington
2002 Henderson and Billie Allen honored with a Pioneer Award at the AUDELCO "VIV" Awards
2003 Little Ham nominated for Drama Desk Award for outstanding orchestration
2003, July 29 Died, New York City
2004 Posthumously honored with a Jazz Masters Award by the National Endowment for the Arts
Scope and Content Note
The Luther Henderson Papers span from the 1930s to 2003 with the majority of the materials dating from 1960 to 1995. The collection includes music manuscripts, subject files, correspondence, business papers, financial documents, photographs, writings, posters, biographical materials, and realia.
The Music series consists of holograph manuscript or computer-generated scores and sketches, manuscript scores in the hands of other composers, lead sheets, parts, and source materials used for arrangements. Most are extensively annotated and are often accompanied by notes, correspondence, and scripts to which they closely relate. From the late 1980s on, Henderson's scores and sketches are almost exclusively computer-generated, although they are freely annotated by hand. Some pieces contain printed file indexes that indicate other works in progress on his computer at the time. Music in the collection is arranged in five subseries: general projects; performer projects; the Luther Henderson Songbook; music library files; and Brick Fleagle music.
Henderson's degree of involvement with musical projects varied widely. In some instances, such as Ain't Misbehavin, he composed the score of the musical and served as music director. In others, such as Flower Drum Song, he contributed only a few arrangements. Henderson also provided musical advice and ideas for projects that later developed into well-known Broadway musicals or for projects that failed to materialize. All of these are represented in the collection. Notable works include Ain't Misbehavin, Ellington Suite, Jelly's Last Jam, MLK Suite, One More Song, Play On!, Reverend Jenkins' Almost All Colored Orphanage Band, and Turned on Broadway. Henderson was a prolific arranger who worked for various performers, such as the Canadian Brass, Placido Domingo, Mandy Patinkin, and the Royal Philharmonic Orchestra. These projects ranged from commissioned works to concerts and night club acts.
The Luther Henderson Songbook is a compilation of vocal and instrumental music that Henderson hoped one day to publish as a multi-volume series. Although he does indicate specific compositions intended for publication, it is likely that that the files contain extraneous tunes that may or may not have had a place in the final product. The remaining musical materials are files of arrangements by other composers that Henderson used for projects or otherwise came to possess, the latter being manuscripts owned by friend and fellow arranger Jacob Roger "Brick" Fleagle. These were presumably bequeathed to Henderson upon Fleagle's death in 1992.
Many projects have accompanying subject files, as do projects that have no music materials but other related documents. The Subject Files series contains correspondence, business papers, royalty statements, scripts, clippings, programs, and/or promotional materials. Loose documents and files not originally associated with subject files are arranged within the Personal Correspondence, Business Papers, Financial Documents, or Miscellany series. Henderson's invoices are particularly useful, as they indicate miscellaneous projects from the 1970s in which he took part. The Brick Fleagle materials contain a scattering of Fleagle's business papers and contracts, many of which relate to his musical arrangements file.
Organization of the Luther Henderson Papers
The Luther Henderson Papers are organized in seven series:
Music, 1940s-2002
Subject Files, 1960-2002
Personal Correspondence, 1953-2002
Business Papers, 1960-2003
Financial Documents, 1964-2003
Miscellany, 1935-2000
Brick Fleagle Materials, 1930s-1987
http://lccn.loc.gov/2011570512
Container List
- Music, 1940s-2002 (Box 1-94, 126-127)
  Scores, sketches, lead sheets, parts, and source materials. Many titles are accompanied by lyric sheets, correspondence, notes, programs, scripts, and other related materials. All projects are musical theater productions or concert works unless indicated otherwise. Musical works with substantial documentation have corresponding subject files.
  - General Projects
    Musical theater productions, concerts, films, recording sessions, individual pieces, and miscellaneous projects.
    Arranged alphabetically by title of project.
    - Ain't misbehavin', 1978, 1988
      - Scores, sketches, lyric sheets, correspondence, and source materials (Box-folder 1/1-2, 52/1)
    - Ain't misbehavin' suite: for chamber orchestra, undated
      - Scores (Box-folder 52/2)
    - The all night strut, 1976
      - Scores, program, and clippings (Box-folder 126/1)
    - Benton and Bowles Inc. [advertisements], 1968-1969, For Avis Radio and Ambush Perfume
      - Scores, sketches, parts, lyric sheets, and notes (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Billy Taylor's 80th birthday celebration [concert], 2002
      - Parts for "I wish I knew how it would feel to be free" (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Black and blue, 1989
      - Scores and sketches (Box-folder 1/5-6, 2/1-2)
    - Black, brown, and beige, undated
      - Score for "The Lord is my shepherd" (Box-folder 52/3)
    - Blow that trumpet, brother, brother!, undated
      - Scores and script (Box-folder 126/2)
    - Bricktop in Paris, 1980
      - Scores and script (Box-folder 126/3)
    - Campbell's Soup [advertisement], 1990
      - Scores, sketches, and correspondence (Box-folder 2/3)
    - Classic Ellington [concert/recording], 1999, 2000
      - Scores, correspondence, notes, and source materials, Includes scores for the Far East suite (Box-folder 2/4-5, 52/4)
    - Come Sunday [recording session], 1994
      - Scores, sketches, parts, and correspondence (Box-folder 52/5)
    - Conquering Thursday, 1969
      - Score for "Prologue" (Box-folder 3/1)
    - The crystal tree, 1981
      - Scores and sketches (Box-folder 3/2-5)
      - Bass and drum parts (Box-folder 4/1-2)
    - Do re mi, 1960
      - Scores for "I know about love" and "Listen baby" (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Ellington suite, 1991
      - Scores, sketches, and source materials (Box-folder 5/1-2)
    - Ellington's New York [concert], 1993
      - Scores, sketches, correspondence, notes, and source materials (Box-folder 5/3-5)
    - Far East suite [recording project], 1999 see Classic Ellington
    - The first, 1981
      - Scores for "Ebbets field" and "There are days" (Box-folder 5/6)
    - Happy New Year, 1980
      - List of musical numbers (Box-folder 5/7)
    - Hey, foxy mama, 1987
      - Scores, sketches, lead sheets, lyric sheets, and notes (Box-folder 52/6-7)
      - Lead sheets (Box-folder 5/8)
    - Jelly's last jam, 1992, Working title: Mr. Jelly Lord
      - Piano-conductor score (Box 6-7)
      - Scores, sketches, lead sheets, lyric sheets, and notes, Materials arranged chronologically, 1989-1992 (Box 8-16, 53, 54/1-5)
      - Parts (Box-folder 17/1-5)
    - Laura, undated, Music and lyrics by Stephen Citron
      - Lead sheets (Box-folder 17/6)
    - The mayor of Harlem, undated
      - Scores, sketches, lyric sheets, and script excerpts (Box-folder 54/6)
    - Miscellany, 1956-1994
      - Scores, Instrumental works; Titles: Brass quintet; A Christmas theme; Ditty a' la Dizzy; Frolic Sam; It's rumor; Story cues (Box-folder 54/7)
      - Score excerpts, sketches and fragments, script excerpts, and notes, Chiefly unidentified materials (Box-folder 17/7)
      - Sketch book, On cover: Early '40s (Box-folder 126/4)
    - MLK suite, 1992
      - Scores and sketches (Box 18-20, 54/8)
      - Parts (Box 21-22)
    - My Broadway, 1998
      - Scores for "Mean to me" and "Not while I'm around" (Box-folder 23/1)
    - Olds FLA '87 [Oldsmobile promotional event], 1987
      - Scores, script, and source materials (Box-folder 23/2-5, 54/9)
    - Olds for '60 [Oldsmobile promotional event], 1959-1960
      - Scores (Box-folder 23/6)
    - Olds for '87 [Oldsmobile promotional event], 1986
      - Scores, sketches, script, correspondence, program, and notes (Box-folder 23/7-9, 54/10)
    - Olds for '88 [Oldsmobile promotional event], 1987
      - Scores, script, notes, program, and source materials (Box 24)
    - Olds for '89 [Oldsmobile promotional event], 1988
      - Scores, vocal parts, and source materials (Box-folder 25/1-3)
    - One more song, 1987, Music and lyrics by Stephen Citron
      - Scores (Box-folder 25/4-5, 26, 27/1-2)
      - Scores of miscellaneous songs (Box 27/3-4, 28/1-3)
      - Lead sheets (Box-folder 28/4-5, 29/1-3)
      - Parts (Box-folder 29/4-6)
    - Play on!, 1997
      - Score (Box-folder 30/1-2)
      - Rehearsal scores (Box-folder 30/3-4, 31/1-4)
      - Sketches and source materials (Box-folder 31/5)
    - Polly, 2000, Stage collaboration with Polly Bergen
      - Rehearsal scores (Box 32)
      - Scores, sketches, lyric sheets, and script excerpts (Box 33)
    - Porgy and Bess suite (brass quintet), 1989
      - Score (Box-folder 34/1)
    - Porgy and Bess suite (brass quintet, orchestra), undated
      - Score (Box-folder 34/2)
      - Parts (Box-folder 34/3-8)
    - Reverend Jenkins' Almost All Colored Orphanage Band, 1987
      - Scores, lead sheets, lyric sheets, notes, and source materials (Box 35)
    - Riviera on the rocks, 1959
      - Scores and lead sheets (Box-folder 36/1-2)
    - Saturday laughter, 1998-1999, Other title: Zuma's journey; Renaissance man
      - Scores, lead sheets, and plot outline (Box-folder 36/3-4)
    - Siren song, undated
      - Scores and lead sheets (Box-folder 36/5)
    - The slams [film], 1973
      - Scores and parts (Box 55-56)
    - Songs my mother never taught me, circa 1979, Earlier title: New phases of 55; Music and lyrics by Stephen Citron
      - Scores, sketches, lead sheets, lyric sheets, script, and notes (Box-folder 36/6-7)
    - St. Louis woman, 1997
      - Scores, sketches, and notes (Box 37, 57/1-2)
    - Stormy weather, 2001
      - Piano-vocal score (Box-folder 38/1-2)
      - Scores and sketches (Box-folder 38/3-6, 39/1-3)
      - Bass parts (Box-folder 39/4)
    - Storyville, 1970s
      - Scores, script excerpts, and notes (Box-folder 57/3-4)
    - Sweeter and sweeter, 1983, Co-written by Leslie Ray
      - Scores, notes, and plot outline (Box-folder 39/5)
    - The three Black kings [ballet], undated, Other title: Les trois rois noirs
      - Scores (Box-folder 58/1, 127/1)
    - Turned on Broadway [recording], 1982
      - Scores for vol. 1 (Box 59, 60/1-2)
      - Parts for vol. 1 (Box 40-42)
      - Scores for vol. 2 (Box 60/3-5, 61)
      - Parts for vol. 2 (Box 43-51)
  - Performer Projects
    Music for concerts, recordings, or night club acts by individual performers or groups.
    Arranged alphabetically by performer last name or name of group.
    - Bergen, Polly see General Projects: Polly
    - Brightman, Sarah, 1988
      - Scores, correspondence, financial documents, and source materials (Box-folder 73/1-5)
    - Burr, Charles, 1976
      - Scores and sketches (Box-folder 73/6)
    - Canadian Brass, circa 1982-1998
      - 12th Street rag
        - Scores (Box-folder 74/1)
      - A-moverin
        - Scores (Box-folder 74/2)
      - Amazing grace
        - Scores (Box-folder 74/3)
      - American Dixieland
        - Sketches and notes (Box-folder 62/1)
      - Andante and Oh, minuetto
        - Scores (Box-folder 74/4)
      - Ballin' the jack
        - Scores and source materials (Box-folder 74/5)
      - Beale Street blues
        - Scores (Box-folder 74/6)
      - Bess, you is my woman
        - Score (Box-folder 62/2)
      - Black bottom stomp
        - Scores (Box-folder 74/7)
      - BMG Classics [recording project]
        - Scores, tuba parts, and correspondence (Box-folder 62/3)
      - Brass on Broadway [recording]
        - Scores, correspondence, and source materials (Box-folder 74/8)
      - The Buttercup-Willow affair
        - Scores and source materials (Box-folder 74/9)
      - By an' by
        - Scores and source materials (Box-folder 74/10)
      - Bye bye baby
        - Score, sketches, and tuba part (Box-folder 62/4)
      - The carousel waltz
        - Scores and source materials (Box-folder 62/5, 75/1)
      - Clockwise permutation
        - Scores and parts (Box-folder 62/6)
      - Deep river
        - Scores and source materials (Box-folder 75/2)
      - Dixie über Alles
        - Scores, correspondence, and source materials (Box-folder 75/3)
      - Don't mean a thing
        - Score and sketches (Box-folder 62/7)
      - Don't mean a thing / Sentimental mood
        - Scores and sketches (Box-folder 62/8)
      - Elegy and celebration
        - Score, sketches, and correspondence (Box-folder 63/1)
      - The Ellington connection [recording project]
        - Scores, correspondence, and source materials (Box-folder 63/2)
      - The entertainer
        - Source materials (Box-folder 63/3)
      - Ezekiel's chariot
        - Scores and source materials (Box-folder 75/5)
      - Fugue for tinhorns
        - Score, sketches, piano part, and source materials (Box-folder 63/4)
      - Germany '96 [concert], Performance in Hamburg, 1996 January 12-13
        - Score, parts, correspondence, and source materials (Box-folder 63/5)
      - Gospel according to the Brass [recording project]
        - Scores, sketches, parts, notes, and source materials (Box-folder 63/6-7, 75/5)
      - A gospel wedding song
        - Score and parts (Box-folder 63/8)
      - High society
        - Scores (Box-folder 75/6-7)
      - Huara-che-roony
        - Scores and parts (Box-folder 63/9)
      - I got rhythm
        - Scores (Box-folder 64/1)
      - Indian love call
        - Scores and source materials (Box-folder 76/1)
      - Inside Ellingtonia [concert]
        - Scores, sketches, correspondence, notes, and source materials (Box-folder 64/2)
      - Jelly and the vamp
        - Scores (Box-folder 76/2)
      - Joy to the world
        - Scores and source materials (Box-folder 76/3)
      - Judith Blegon [concert]
        - Sketches, notes, and source materials (Box-folder 64/3)
      - King Porter stomp
        - Scores and source materials (Box-folder 76/4)
      - London blues, Other title: Shoe shiner's drag
        - Scores and source materials (Box-folder 76/5)
      - Loudly let the trumpet bray
        - Scores and source materials (Box-folder 76/6)
      - Lush life
        - Score and parts (Box-folder 64/4)
      - MacDonald's Band
        - Scores, sketches, and parts (Box-folder 64/5)
      - Mamie's blues
        - Scores and source materials (Box-folder 76/7)
      - Maple leaf rag
        - Score and source materials (Box-folder 64/6)
      - McDonald's in brass [advertisement]
        - Scores and source materials (Box-folder 76/8)
      - Memory
        - Score and sketches (Box-folder 64/7)
      - Minuet in blue-hoo
        - Score and parts (Box-folder 65/1)
      - Music of the night
        - Score, sketches, and source materials (Box-folder 65/2)
      - My dearest love
        - Scores (Box-folder 76/9)
      - Nearer to thee
        - Scores and sketches (Box-folder 65/3)
      - New world a comin'
        - Scores, sketches, correspondence, and source materials (Box-folder 65/4)
      - O say can you
        - Scores, correspondence, and notes (Box-folder 76/10)
      - The pearls
        - Scores and sketches (Box-folder 76/11)
      - Poor butterfly see also BMG Classics
        - Score, trumpet parts, and source materials (Box-folder 65/5)
      - The race
        - Scores (Box-folder 77/1)
      - Red hot jazz: the Dixieland album [recording]
        - Scores (Box-folder 65/6-7)
      - Red velvet brass
        - Scores and source materials (Box-folder 65/8)
      - The rhythm series
        - Score (Box-folder 65/9)
      - Rondo-boperation
        - Score and parts (Box-folder 77/2)
      - The saints' hallelujah
        - Score (Box-folder 66/1, 77/3)
      - Send in the clowns
        - Score, sketches, and source materials (Box-folder 66/2)
      - Sentimental mood
        - Scores (Box-folder 66/3)
      - Seventy-six trombones
        - Score and sketches (Box-folder 66/4)
      - Slaughter on 10th Ave.
        - Scores and source materials (Box-folder 77/4-5)
      - Softly as in a morning sunrise
        - Scores and source materials (Box-folder 77/6)
      - Sophisticated lady
        - Scores, sketches, and correspondence (Box-folder 66/5)
      - St. Louis blues
        - Scores (Box-folder 77/7)
      - The Strayhorn suite
        - Score and source materials for "Blood count" (Box-folder 66/6)
      - Strike up the band
        - Score (Box-folder 66/7)
      - Strike up the band [recording]
        - Scores (Box-folder 66/8)
      - Study war no more
        - Scores (Box-folder 77/8)
      - Sugar blues see also BMG Classics
        - Parts and source materials (Box-folder 67/1)
      - Take his hand
        - Score (Box-folder 67/2)
      - What child is this?
        - Scores and source materials (Box-folder 77/9)
      - The wolverines
        - Scores, sketches, and source materials (Box-folder 77/10)
      - You made me love you
        - Scores (Box-folder 77/11)
      - You name it
        - Score and parts (Box-folder 67/3)
    - Cook, Barbara, 1987
      - Scores for "Sooner or later" (Box-folder 78/1)
    - Dietz and Schwartz, 1972
      - Sketches, lyric sheets, notes, and source materials (Box-folder 67/4)
    - Domingo, Placido, 1991
      - Scores, notes, and source materials (Box-folder 67/5)
    - Ellis, Anita, 1992-1993
      - Scores, lead sheets, correspondence, photographs, notes, and source materials (Box-folder 67/6)
    - Goulet, Robert and Carol, 1966
      - Scores and notes (Box-folder 67/7)
    - Henderson, Margo, 1977-1978 and undated
      - Scores, parts, promotional materials, notes, and miscellany, Chiefly materials for an event at the Rainbow Grill, NY, 1978 (Box-folder 68-70/4, 78/2)
    - Henderson, Melanie, 1966 and undated
      - Scores and lyric sheets, Mostly songs by Melanie Henderson in Luther Henderson's hand (Box-folder 70/5)
    - Johnson, Betty, 1983-1985
      - Scores, notes, and source materials (Box-folder 71/1-3)
    - Lawrence, Carol, 1962, 1965 and undated
      - Scores and notes, Includes "Shaking the blues away", written for the 1962 Christmas episode of the Ed Sullivan Show (Box-folder 71/4-5, 78/3)
    - Patinkin, Mandy, 1988
      - Scores and source materials (Box-folder 78/4-6, 79)
    - Royal Philharmonic Orchestra, 1987-1988
      - Andrew Lloyd Weber suite
        - Scores (Box-folder 80/1)
      - Another hundred people with fidgety feet
        - Scores (Box-folder 80/2)
      - Cole Porter suite. Overture
        - Scores (Box-folder 72/1)
      - Harold Arlen suite
        - Scores (Box-folder 72/2, 80/3-4)
        - Parts (Box-folder 80/5-7)
      - Hart and Hammerstein by Rodgers
        - Scores (Box-folder 81/1-2)
        - Parts for 3rd movement (Box-folder 81/3)
      - Jesus Christ superstar: instrumental suite
        - Scores (Box-folder 81/4-5)
        - Source materials and notes (Box-folder 72/3)
      - Jule Styne suite
        - Scores (Box-folder 72/4, 82/1-2)
        - Parts (Box-folder 82/3-5)
      - Phantom of the opera: orchestra suite
        - Scores (Box-folder 83/1-3)
        - Source materials and notes (Box-folder 72/5)